Okay בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף daf officially 33, we pick
up
ל''ב ע''א. lamed bet amud aleph. We are towards the bottom and
we pick up with the following:
ועתה תנו רבנן. ve-ata tanu rabanan. About the middle of the page,
about six lines after the גמרא Gemara begins, and we are dealing
with the case about this issue about somebody who, again, two brothers,
two sisters,
and that even if the one of them, and then one brother
dies, so she's אחות אשה, achot isha,
and then even if the second guy's wife dies, she remains אחות
אשה. achot isha. Okay, nothing too new from what we've seen, but
now although not so much new in the משנה, Mishnah, the גמרא
Gemara is going to introduce a ברייתא braita which is going to
get us on a major discussion taking us in a very different
area. So let's take a look. תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. About six
lines below where the גמרא Gemara begins on ל''ב ע''א. lamed bet
amud aleph. בא
עליה, ba aleha,
let's say, forget this whole fancy case, a man basically,
somebody was married to a person's, a person's brother married his wife's
sister. All right, and then the guy died, let's even assume, thank
you, let's even assume no מצות יבום, mitzvat yibum, who knows, there
were kids. Forget יבום. yibum. So this is a woman that's both
this man's brother's wife and wife's sister. Two prohibitions. And he has
sex with her. What's the story? בא עליה חייב עליה משום אשת
אח ומשום אחות אשה דברי רבי יוסי. ba aleha chayav aleha mishum
eshet ach u-mishum achot isha divrei Rabbi Yose. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose
says a reasonable thing, he transgressed two prohibitions: it's both his brother's
wife and his wife's sister. Fine. רבי שמעון אומר אינו חייב אלא
משום אשת אח בלבד. Rabbi Shimon omer eino chayav ela mishum eshet
ach bilvad. No, he only transgressed brother's wife, he doesn't transgress wife's
sister. Why not? She is both. So the גמרא Gemara says ותניא,
ve-tanya, so before we even analyze it first we have to deal
with a contradiction. רבי שמעון אומר אינו חייב אלא משום אחות אשה
בלבד. Rabbi Shimon omer eino chayav ela mishum achot isha bilvad. You
only transgress wife's sister. So רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon clearly has an
idea that you're only transgressing one. But first of all why, and
second of all according to one version it's only brother's wife and
according to the other version it's only wife's sister and this woman
is both. So what's the explanation? So now that we'll reconcile this
problem we'll see what the reason behind it is. So the גמרא
Gemara is לא קשיא. lo kashya. כאן שנשא חי ואחר כך נשא
מת, kan she-nasa chay ve-acharkach nasa met, in one case first the
surviving brother married her and then the dead brother, not when he
was dead but who now is dead married her. And in the
other case כאן שנשא מת ואחר כך נשא חי, kan she-nasa met
ve-acharkach nasa chay, it was the reverse. What does that mean? It
means, and again, no יבום, yibum, I'm not talking about יבום yibum
for today, believe it or not. We are talking about brothers and
sisters but we're not talking about יבום, yibum, okay? So you've got,
okay, everybody has kids let's say, okay? Don't worry about יבום, yibum,
everybody's got kids. All right, so you've got ראובן Reuven is married
to רחל Rachel and שמעון Shimon is married to
לאה. Leah. Happily married, lots of kids, ראובן Reuven dies. Okay, so
רחל Rachel is both אשת אח eshet ach and אחות אשה, achot
isha, okay? And רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
only transgresses one if he sleeps with רחל. Rachel. Why? So it
says here's the difference. ראובן Reuven is the מת, met, the guy
who eventually dies, okay? So if first ראובן Reuven married רחל Rachel
before they were married, what does רחל Rachel become first to שמעון?
Shimon? אשת אח. eshet ach. Then שמעון Shimon marries לאה, Leah, so
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says you go by the first definition. Why?
We'll see. אין איסור חל על איסור. ein issur chal al issur.
So she's only אשת אח. eshet ach. That's if נשא מת ואחר
כך נשא חי, nasa met ve-acharkach nasa chay, she's אשת אח. eshet
ach. Let's say it's the reverse. שמעון Shimon is first married to
לאה, Leah, okay? What is רחל Rachel now to שמעון? Shimon? אחות
אשה. achot isha. Then he marries her, so she remains אחות אשה.
achot isha. So that's נשא חי ואחר כך נשא מת, nasa chay
ve-acharkach nasa met, okay?
So רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says you only get the first definition
which is a concept of אין איסור חל על איסור. ein issur
chal al issur. One status of prohibition does not take effect on
top of another one. And so which one takes effect? The one
that was there first, okay? This is the first one, the second
one does not take a place on top of the first. So
it goes all by the first status. So that's רבי שמעון's Rabbi
Shimon idea that there's only one, and the contradiction is which is
the one that was first. All right, so let's take a look
now at the גמרא. Gemara. So this is what we're going to
be into for all of today. No יבום, yibum, it's the question
of איסור חל על איסור. issur chal al issur. What?
Are they both כרת? karet?
Are they both כרת? karet? Yes, they're both כרת. karet.
So what's the difference?
Oh, so good question, good question. Yeah, you're going to hell either
way. The difference is if it were בשוגג beshogeg do you bring
one קרבן korban or two קרבנות? korbanot? Okay? And there might be
other differences too but that's an excellent point. Yes.
Does אין איסור חל על איסור ein issur chal al issur apply
to those examples where it's like יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* a guy
eats בשר בחלב *basar b'chalav*? It's all piled up on top.
Yes. Okay. So or I should say maybe, but those are part
of the discussion. Okay, so גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. לא
קשיא kashya. כאן שנשא זה וחזר ונשא מת כאן שנשא מת וחזר
ונשא זה *Lo kashya kan shenasa ze v'chazar v'nasa mes kan shenasa
mes v'chazar v'nasa ze*. For Rabbi Shimon says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*,
now Rabbi Shimon who says only one. היכא דנשא מת וחזר ונשא
חי *Hecha d'nasa mes v'chazar v'nasa chai*. First the dead guy, Reuven
married her, so she began by being אשת אח aishet ach, *eshes
ach*. And then he married Leah, so then it was אחות אשה
achos isha *achos isha*. כיון דאיסור אחות אשה לא חייל *Keivan d'isur
achos isha lo chayeil*, since Rachel never became אחות אשה *achos isha*,
תתייבם מייבומי *tisyabem miyibumei*.
So we've got a question. How according to Rabbi Shimon, this is
a classic case, if there are no kids, where there's no מצות
ייבום *mitzvas yibum*, because Rachel is an ערוה *erva*. Says, wait a
minute, according to Rabbi Shimon, why is Rachel an ערוה *erva*? Okay,
he first marries Rachel, then he marries Leah, you're telling me Rachel
is only אשת אח *eshes ach*, because that was her first status.
So now if Reuven dies with no kids, go ahead and do
ייבום *yibum* with Rachel, she's not your wife's sister, she's only אשת
אח *eshes ach*.
That's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to say, okay, because
as soon as you allow for ייבום *yibum*, then אשת אח *eshes
ach* goes away and then she becomes אחות אשה *achos isha*. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, אמר רב אשי איסור issur אחות אשה
מטלא טלי וקאי *Amar Rav Ashi isur achos isha matla tali v'kai*.
It's not like wife's sister is not a relevant concept. It's hovering
above, okay,
it's an appropriate status, it just can't take effect because there's a
pre-existing one. So therefore, אי פקע איסור issur. אשת אח *ei paka
isur eshes ach*, if the status of wife's brother were to go
away—brother's wife were to go away because there would be a מצות
ייבום *mitzvas yibum*, so then אתי איסור issur אחות אשה וחייל *asi
isur achos isha v'chayeil*, then she would all of a sudden become
now wife's sister, so
and that prohibition would apply, so you can't do ייבום *yibum*. ייבום
*Yibum* would turn her into an ערוה *erva*. והשתא לא פקע *v'hashta
lo paka*, and therefore, because it can't go away, because it would
just invite the next one, it doesn't go away, okay, which interestingly
then also means that, you know, then the sister then the other
wives are צרת ערוה *tzaras erva* and all these things, even though
right now she's not an ערוה *erva*, but because she would become
an ערוה *erva* were there to be a מצות ייבום *mitzvas yibum*,
there's no מצות ייבום *mitzvas yibum*, and therefore she remains the איסור
issur ערוה *isur erva* of אשת אח *eshes ach* even when there
are no kids. Alright, so that's fascinating in itself, that type of
mechanism, but now we're going to go back to the issue of
איסור חל על איסור issur chal al issur *isur chal al isur*.
וסבר רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi איסור חל על איסור issur chal al
issur. *V'savar Rabbi Yosi isur chal al isur*? So now Rabbi Yosi
says she has both definitions. So does Rabbi Yosi really hold that
one איסור issur *isur* takes effect on the other one? והתניא *V'hanya*,
we taught in a ברייתא *braisa*. עבר עבירה שיש בה שתי מיתות
*Avar aveira sheyesh ba shtei misos*. If somebody did a sin that
has two, you know, two liable in two death penalties. נידון
בחמורה *Nidon b'chamura*. So then the question is, it's like a סנהדרין
*Sanhedrin* type of a question, which is, which of the מיתות *misos*
do you give? There are ארבע מיתות בית דין Beis Din *arba
misos beis din*, and some are seen as more weighty than others.
So the הלכה halakha *halacha* is, if somebody did a sin and
is deserving of two, you give them the more weighty death penalty.
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi אומר נידון בזיקה הראשונה הבאה עליו *Rabbi Yosi
omer nidon b'zika harishona habaa alav*. No, you go by the first
relationship. There's that word זיקה *zika* again. תניא *Tanya*, then we taught
in a ברייתא *braisa*. כיצד *Keitzad*, what how would this play out?
אמר רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi נידון בזיקה הראשונה הבאה עליו *Amar Rabbi
Yosi nidon b'zika harishona habaa alav*. So, חמותו ונעשית אשת איש *chamoso
v'naasis eshes ish*. Now a mother-in-law is punishable by שריפה *sreifa*, which
is a weighty death penalty. אשת איש *eshes ish*, a simple case
of adultery is punishable by חנק chenek *chenek*, which is considered a
less weighty form of execution. Okay, so חמותו *chamoso* is the weightier
one. So according, so let's say a woman is both a man's
mother-in-law and a married woman. That's an easy scenario, right? His mother-in-law
is married, so to his presumably his father-in-law. So anyway, in that
case, she's mother-in-law and a married woman. So the תנא קמא *Tanna
Kamma* would say, so he gets punished by שריפה *sreifa* because that's
the weightier—the mother-in-law status is the weightier one, is the one—is the
weightier death penalty. Rabbi Yosi says, no, only by the first way
the relationship was defined. What does that mean? כיצד נידון בזיקה הראשונה
הבאה עליו *Keitzad nidon b'zika harishona habaa alav*? חמותו ונעשית אשת איש
*Chamoso v'naasis eshes ish*. Let's say she first was his mother-in-law and
then she became a married woman. How could that be? His wife's
mother was divorced or widowed. So first this woman was his mother-in-law,
and then she got married. So the first definition that she had
to him was mother-in-law. So in that case, he gets punished by
שריפה *sreifa*.
Okay. אשת איש ונעשית חמותו *Eshes ish v'naasis chamoso*, which is also
a very reasonable
scenario—this woman was married, and then he married her daughter. So first
this woman was a married woman, before he ever, right, got married
to her daughter, she was forbidden to him as a married woman,
and then he married her daughter. So in that type of a
case, the first status is married woman, mother-in-law comes later. So in
that case, נידון באשת איש *nidon b'eshes ish*, then she's אשת איש
*eshes ish*. sleeps with her, if it's sleeping with a married woman,
it's not sleeping with his mother-in-law and it's punishable by the lesser
actually, by חנק and not by שרפה. sreifa. So he says basically
the only logic to say give the weaker one is because you
are saying that the other one doesn't exist. I mean the only
the only logic the only way to allow him to say חנק
and not שרפה sreifa is because he says you're not punishable by
שרפה, sreifa, right? Because if you really were both, you'd get the
more serious punishment. So clearly he is saying, and that's the language,
נידון בזיקה ראשונה. niddun be-zika rishona. This is an idea of אין
איסור חל על איסור. ein issur chal al issur. We're not going
to define it as both prohibitions, we're going to define it as
the first prohibition, the one that first defined your relationship to this
woman. So now we've got this problem. The same רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yosi that says a woman who is wife's sister and brother's wife
is both punishments, both definitions, says that a woman who is married
woman and mother-in-law is only goes by the first definition. So which
one does רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei say? Does he say איסור חל
על איסור issur chal al issur, or אין איסור חל על איסור?
ein issur chal al issur? So let's see what the גמרא Gemara
says. אמר רבי אבהו מודה רבי יוסי באיסור מוסיף. Amar Rabbi Abahu
modeh Rabbi Yossi be-issur mosif. All right, now we're getting into the
real sort of heart of the discussions of איסור חל על איסור.
issur chal al issur There are two ideas, or actually three that
we're going to see today.
I have, thank you. So there's איסור מוסיף, issur mosif,
which is
okay,
איסור כולל, issur kolel, doesn't mean it's אסור assur to go into
a כולל, kollel, and and בת אחת. bat achas. Okay, בת אחת
bat
achas we're going to deal with later. בת אחת bat achas just
means that you don't you can't say the first one because they
take because they both took effect at the same time. Okay, so
we won't worry about that right now. איסור כולל, issur kolel, איסור
מוסיף. issur mosif. What is the difference? All right, איסור כולל issur
kolel means it is of it broadens the scope. You've got something
that's forbidden, the second איסור issur? came along and that actually made
this person, thing, object, whatever, forbidden to a wider scope of people.
So for example, let's talk about mother-in-law and married woman. Which do
they have equal scope in terms of the people that they are
that that are forbidden? No. Married woman is אסורה asura to who?
Everybody. Mother-in-law is only אסורה asura to son-in-law. So if it started
with mother-in-law and then became married woman, right? So then that's a
איסור כולל issur kolel and that therefore could apply to... right, I
mean an איסור מוסיף. issur mosif. An איסור מוסיף issur mosif is
a broader scope, more people and that could take effect. If it
started with married woman
and
then became mother-in-law, that's a narrower scope that doesn't take effect. Okay,
so that actually would so that's what we're saying. Now how does
that solve it? Because we're not trying to solve the mother-in-law case,
we're trying to solve this case. Okay, so let's talk about it.
Brother's wife and and and wife's sister. Which one has the broader
scope?
Well it depends, I mean, doesn't one's בחייה? be-chayeha? Right?
No, that's duration, that's not scope.
Brother's wife. Brother's wife is forbidden to the other brothers as well.
Okay, so how could רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei say here that you
get both? Well it depends on the order. If it first started
with wife's sister, that's a narrower scope. Then ראובן Reuven married רחל,
Rachel, she became forbidden to all the brothers, that's a broader scope,
that's an איסור מוסיף, issur mosif, and then it could also be
both. So you could get both here if the order was first
wife's sister and then brother's wife.
Only in the case of more than one brother, if the case
is two...
So the גמרא Gemara seems to not care whether in practice there
are more brothers. Anyway, another brother could be born. At least conceptually
it's a prohibition that applies to a broader scope of people. Okay,
but that's a good point but the גמרא Gemara doesn't seem to
care. So why can we say both here? Yes, generally אין איסור
חל על איסור ein issur chal al issur unless the second one
has broader scope. So you could get two here if the order
started with אחות אשה and then she got married to the brother
and then it got brought in. In the case of mother-in-law and
married woman, right, if mother-in-law comes,
if married woman comes first, you're never going to get him mother-in-law,
mother-in-law is the weightier one, you're never going to get him for
mother-in-law, because married woman is already the broader scope. So that's why
he says you'll never punish the guy by שרפה sreifa if married
woman comes first, because mother-in-law is a narrower scope, it won't take
effect. But in this case you can get the guy for both
as long as wife's sister comes first, then brother's wife is broader
and then that you can get him for both.
So you're trying to make absolutely sure you've been defining איסור מוסיף,
issur mosif, not איסור כולל. issur kolel.
Correct. We haven't got to איסור כולל issur kolel yet.
Okay, so let's put that away.
איסור מוסיף issur mosif is broader, right, broader scope of like of
people, people prohibited.
Correct. For now we are not going to worry about things like
duration, severity, okay? It's complicated enough as it is, so we're going
to go with so far what the גמרא Gemara says. Okay, so
let's take a look.
Okay. מודה רבי יוסי באיסור מוסיף. Modeh Rabbi Yosi be-issur mosif. תינח,
Teinach, and he says fine, that will work היכא דנסב חי ואחר
כך נסב מת. heicha de-nasa chai ve-achar kach nasa meis. First,
the surviving brother, whatever, Shimon married, so it started by being wife's
sister,
and then the guy who's going to die married her, married the,
married the, married the other one, and then she became brother's wife.
So if it starts with wife's sister and then becomes brother's wife,
that's a larger scope, then you have both. מיגו דאיתוסף איסור לגבי
אחים, Migo de-itosif issur legabei achim,
since now Rachel is forbidden also to all other brothers, תוסיף איסור
לגבי דידיה, to-isif issur legabei dideih, so she also becomes forbidden once
already this new status, here's a way of conceptually thinking about it.
The new status takes effect on Rachel because it has relevance to
other people. It might not have relevance to Shimon. She was already
אסור assur to Shimon. But it has potential relevance to other people,
either brothers or brothers who might be born. Okay, now Michael's going
to ask what if the father is dead so there are no
brothers who could be born, my mother is dead. Fine. Doesn't matter.
In theory, okay, it has relevance to other people and because this
new status can have relevance to other people, it also has relevance
even to Shimon, even though she was already אסור assur to Shimon.
Okay, that's איסור מוסיף. issur mosif. Okay,
so that works if she started as wife's sister and then became
brother's wife. אלא היכא דנסב מת ואחר כך נסב חי, Ella heicha
de-nasa meis ve-achar kach nasa chai, if it was reversed, first she
was brother's wife and then she was wife's sister, so why in
that case would רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei say that you get both
statuses? מאי איסור מוסיף איכא? Mai issur mosif ika? Wife's sister isn't
adding any prohibitions. Okay, she's already brother's wife, אסור assur to all
the brothers, or any, not prohibitions, any people. וכי תימא, Ve-chi teima,
maybe you'll say מיגו דאיתסר בכולהו אחוותא, migo de-itsar bekulu achvata, maybe,
ah,
here's what happens. She started off as brother's wife and then, and
then Shimon married Leah. So now she is forbidden to, not she
is actually, Shimon is forbidden not just to Rachel, but now that
Shimon married Leah, who else is Shimon forbidden to?
Any other sisters that might exist. And of course there might not
be any other sisters again, that doesn't matter. In theory, Shimon now
by marrying Leah is אסור assur in more, in all sisters. Now,
that's not the same. That's what I'm saying. Rachel used to be
married to this scope of, אסור assur to this scope of people,
now she's אסור assur to a wider scope of people, right? That's
איסור מוסיף. issur mosif. It used to be a narrow scope, this
new status makes her forbidden to a wider
scope of people that she's אסור assur to. You start with the
forbidden thing, okay? איסור מוסיף. Issur mosif. איסור כולל, Issur kollel, having
too much fun with my markers and their colors.
Okay, anyway,
איסור כולל, issur kollel, what's איסור כולל? issur kollel? איסור כולל Issur
kollel is that you basically have here, right, Rachel
and here's Shimon, okay? So Rachel remains just as, you know, she
started, she started, right, by being forbidden here to like all the
brothers. She was אשת אח, these are all the brothers. Okay, that's
where you started. Okay? Then Shimon goes ahead and marries Leah, right?
He goes ahead and marries Leah. He now is אסור, assur, Shimon
in the until now was אסור assur just to Rachel. Now that
he's married Leah, he's also אסור assur to all the sisters. Okay?
Right?
So you see the difference.
Right here, Rachel herself
that was אסור assur at the second stage became אסור assur to
more people. Since she's אסור assur to more people, right, in this
scenario where first she was a sister, a wife's sister and then
a brother's wife, because she became אסור assur right to more brothers,
here she was just married to, here she was just אסור assur
to Shimon and then she became אסור assur not just to Shimon
but to all the brothers.
Why is that?
Okay, because first, first she was wife's sister and then she became
brother's wife.
First she was wife's sister.
Right, once she'd then be marry the brother, she wasn't just אסור
assur to שמעון, Shimon, she was אסור assur to all the brothers.
So C now is אסור assur to more people, so now she
gets a status of brother's wife to the other brothers, she'll get
the status of brother's wife even to שמעון. Shimon. That makes a
lot of sense, right? Because what happens is he married the brother,
she's considered brother's wife to these other guys, so she's also considered
brother's wife to שמעון. Shimon. So the that's adding the scope, broadening
the scope to who she's אסור, assur, therefore it applies into שמעון.
Shimon. This is less obvious. Okay, here her status hasn't changed. She
was אסור assur to all the brothers, she remains אסור assur to
all the brothers. Okay, her status hasn't changed. But what has changed
is שמעון Shimon used to be אסור assur just to her and
now he's אסור assur to all the sisters. So since these other
sisters are now forbidden to him, right, should we say that since
they're forbidden to him, she should become forbidden to him as well
with this new definition?
She becomes part of a larger כלל. klal.
She becomes larger
כלל, klal, right, broadening.
No, her status, her, she is not אסור assur to anybody more
than she was אסור assur before. Okay, so her status has not
changed. People to the left and right of her have changed. Her
sisters now are אסור, assur, and she's part of her sisters. So
does the fact that her sisters are אסור assur also sweep her
away and make her considered to be in that status as well
and אסור assur with that new definition? This is clearly more obvious.
Her own status changed, right? She started off just being אסור assur
to שמעון, Shimon, then she married the brother and now she's אסור
assur to all the brothers. That's a new definition that directly applies
to her that impacts the other brothers. If it's a new definition
that's true to her now, brother's wife, that has relevance to other
brothers, let it have relevance to שמעון Shimon as well. Here her
whole status has changed. Here her status didn't change, her sisters' status
is changed. But since her sisters' status have changed and she's part
of her sisters, maybe that'll make her status change as well. Yes.
So if you look at it from רחל's Rachel perspective, it's exactly
backwards, right? I mean, what is for him איסור מוסיף, issur mosif,
for her is איסור כולל, issur kolel, and vice versa.
For she he becomes part of a larger כלל klal of people
that
no because in this case she's not אסור assur to any more
people. Meaning, if you're asking who can she have sex with, before
she couldn't have sex with the brothers and now she can't have
sex with the brothers.
Nothing it doesn't
this doesn't affect
her because
שמעון Shimon still
has the
different yeah yeah yes in other words איסור מוסיף issur mosif רחל
Rachel has now become אסור assur to more
people, איסור כולל issur kolel רחל Rachel now finds herself amongst a
larger population of people who are participating in the same thing.
Correct.
Exactly. Okay.
All right. Now we got those. If you got those you are
so far ahead of the game.
I can't even afford to go to a כולל. kolel.
Exactly. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this:
וכי תימא V'chi teima lest you say מדאיכא בכולהו אחוותא, mid-d'ika b'khulach
achvasa, now
that
there was שמעון Shimon married the sister, all of the sisters are
now forbidden to
שמעון. Shimon. האי איסור כולל הוא, Hai issur kolel hu, that's an
איסור מוסיף, issur mosif, that's an איסור כולל, issur kolel, and therefore
why should that create a double status? She's not new אסור assur
to more people, just other people in her class are אסור. assur.
אלא אמר רבא, Ela amar Rava, רבא Rava so רבא Rava says
you know what you're right. So of course we could have said
maybe that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei holds of איסור כולל, issur kolel,
but then it wouldn't work for the whole case of mother-in-law and
married wife etc. So we're stuck, right? So how do you explain
why רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi. says both cases? So the גמרא Gemara
says that you get both statuses of wife's sister and brother's wife.
אלא אמר רבא מעלה אני עליו כאילו עשה שתים בין חייב אלא
אחת. Ela amar Rava ma'aleh ani alav k'ilu asah shtayim bein chayav
ela achas. So רבא Rava says you know what okay fine you're
right. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi would hold in the reverse case you
really would only get because he really only holds of איסור מוסיף,
issur mosif, he doesn't hold of איסור כולל issur kolel because that's
clear because of the case about mother-in-law and married woman he there
are cases where you only get the the married woman status and
you don't get the second status. So he's not going to hold
you can sort of get the second thing to come one way
or the other. So why by the case of brother's wife and
wife's sisters does he say you transgress both? He doesn't mean literally.
He doesn't mean technically in terms of the actual punishment we'll impose
like two קרבנות korbanot or two series of lashes or two death
penalties. Okay, he doesn't mean that in that way you did both.
He means you deserve to get punished for both, it's as if
you transgressed both. Of course like what type of a halakhic statement
therefore is that, what type of a meaningful statement is that as
all right מעלה
אני עליו כאילו עשה שתים ma'aleh ani alav k'ilu asah shtayim so
then what way is he actually even arguing with רבי שמעון? Rabbi
Shimon? רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says oh it's not like you transgressed
two things, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says it is like you transgressed
two things. Who the heck cares, what is like... Like mean anyway,
right? So one way of thinking about what this means is, right,
if I strip the idea of punishment from it, let's pretend that
there was never any punishments in the תורה, Torah, right? Would I
say you transgressed two עבירות averos or not? Okay, when we say
אין איסור חל על איסור, ein issur chal al issur, does that
mean that you literally didn't transgress the prohibition of wife's sister? I
mean she's your wife's sister. No, you didn't transgress it? Or do
we say you transgressed it, but maybe there are no consequences to
it. The halakhic consequences are all defined by the first status. So
whatever the consequences might be, lashes, a קרבן, korban, you know, a
certain type of a death penalty, that doesn't, that all is defined
by the first status. So but maybe even if we say אין
איסור חל על איסור, ein issur chal al issur, maybe you still
are transgressing, just without consequences. That might be what this means. Okay,
but this now becomes a weaker answer. We have רב יוסי Reb
Yose by the case of mother-in-law who is married woman and he
says you only get one. We have the case about sister-in-law who's
also wife's sister. And he says you get two. So the גמרא
Gemara says if it's in a certain order, I can understand why
you get two. If it's in the other order, I can't understand
it. And the גמרא Gemara answers, alright, you're right. You really don't
get two in that other case, but it's like you get two.
מעלה אני עליו כאילו עשה שתים. Ma'aleh ani alav ke'ilu asah shta'im.
Very interesting answer. וכן כי אתא רבין אמר רבי יוחנן מעלה אני
עליו כאילו עשה שתים ואינו חייב אלא אחת. Ve'chen ki ata Ravin
amar Reb Yochanan ma'aleh ani alav ke'ilu asah shta'im ve'eino chayav ela
achat. מאי נפקא מינה? Mai nafka mina?
So the גמרא Gemara does not like this idea of it's as
if you. Who cares as if, what does that mean anyway? And
if he is arguing with רב שמעון, Reb Shimon, there's got to
be some relevance to the discussion. So מאי נפקא מינה? Mai nafka
mina? לקוברו בין רשעים גמורים. Likvoro bein resha'im gemurim.
The מאי נפקא מינה nafka mina is to bury amongst fully wicked
people. Okay, because based on how much of a רשע rasha a
person is depends on where they get buried in the cemetery. ובפלוגתא,
Uviflukta, now because there's a whole issue that somebody you know, when
בית דין executes somebody, the more weighty punishments, they get buried in
one section, when they execute him the more lighter executions, he gets
buried in another section. So this guy is treated, if you want
to use the בריסקער Brisker terminology,
בגברא, begavra, in terms of his like personal status and identity, as
if he did two עבירות. averos. Even though in terms of the
actual punishment and consequence of that act, he's not going to get
punished, but in terms of what it says about him as a
person, it is like there are two. Again, very funny and what
exactly type of debate that is with רב שמעון Reb Shimon is
not exactly clear. Okay, but what we had introduced is the idea
of רב שמעון Reb Shimon saying categorically אין איסור חל על איסור,
ein issur chal al issur, רב יוסי Reb Yose saying there are
times you could have איסור חל על איסור, issur chal al issur,
and the גמרא Gemara identifying those times as when it is an
איסור מוסיף, issur mosif, when the second one broadens the scope that
that first person was forbidden to. Now that person is forbidden to
a broader scope of people and therefore the status changes for that,
even with the second איסור. issur Yes.
I can imagine אין איסור חל על איסור ein issur chal al
issur the following way. It's actually, it's like items in a vending
machine, right? There's packs on top of each other. Yeah. You can't
get at the second one before
the first one is moved. That's a way of thinking about it,
certainly. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, ובפלוגתא. uviflukta. This issue, this issue of איסור חל על איסור
issur chal al issur and איסור מוסיף issur mosif etc. is connected
to another debate. And let's take a look, and this hopefully will
read pretty quickly. איתמר, Itmar, it was taught. זר ששימש בשבת. Zar
sheshimush beshabbos. You have a non כהן kohen who works in the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash on שבת. Shabbos. Now what's the normal הלכה
halakha about a non כהן kohen who works in the בית המקדש?
Beis Hamikdash? חייב מיתה, chayav misa, okay, at least בידי שמים. bidei
shamayim. What's the normal הלכה halacha about somebody who does מלאכה melacha
on שבת? Shabbos? חייב מיתה chayav misa בידי אדם bidei adam actually.
So here he goes and he works in the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash on שבת. Shabbos. Is he חייב מיתה chayav misa twice? Because
of a non כהן kohen who works in the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash and as a non כהן kohen he's not allowed to work,
if he were כהן kohen he could work in the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash on שבת. Shabbos. As a non כהן kohen he's not
allowed to. So he's חייב מיתה chayav misa for חילול שבת, chilul
shabbos, or only one. So let's take a look. זר ששימש בשבת.
Zar sheshimush beshabbos.
רב חייא Reb Chiya אמר חייב שתים. amar chayav shta'im. בר קפרא
Bar Kappara אמר אינו חייב אלא אחת. amar eino chayav ela achat.
קפץ Kafatz רב חייא Reb Chiya ונשבע. venishba. העבודה! Ha'avodah!
Which is very, it's like cute because עבודה avodah means the service
in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, but it's also a way of
taking an oath. By the service, by the divine service. כך שמעתי
מרבי שתים. kach shamati me-Rabbi shtayim. I heard this from רבי—רבי יהודה
הנשיא—שתים, that if somebody, if a זר zar serves in the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash on שבת Shabbos he's חייב chayav twice.
קפץ בר קפרא ונשבע. העבודה! כך שמעתי מרבי אחת. Kofatz Bar Kappara
v'nishba ha'avoda kach shamati me'rebi achas. I took an oath, he said
I heard the exact opposite from רבי, Rebbi I heard only אחת.
achat. That was one debate. התחיל Hitchil רב חייא Reb Chiya לדון.
ladun. So רב חייא Reb Chiya said let's try to figure this
out. Okay, we got two opposing opinions, nobody's backing down. Let's try
to figure it out. Okay, let's be reasonable, let's use some reason
here. שבת לכל נאסרה. Shabbos lechol nesra. שבת Shabbos is forbidden to
everybody.
כשהותרה במקדש, keshe-hutra be-mikdash when it was permitted in the בית המקדש,
Beis Hamikdash, you don't have to worry about שבת, Shabbos, אצל כהנים
הותרה. etzel kohanim hutra. It was said for כוהנים, Kohanim, כוהנים Kohanim
get a dispensation. לכוהנים הותרה ולא לזרים, L'kohanim hutra v'lo l'zarim, the
dispensation only applied to כוהנים, Kohanim, not to non-כוהנים. Kohanim. So this
person transgresses both for a non-כוהן Kohen who does the עבודה Avoda
and for שבת, Shabbos, he never got a dispensation. Okay, יש כאן
משום זרות ויש כאן משום שבת. Yesh kan mishum zarus v'yesh kan
mishum Shabbos. So he says, "That's my logic, that's a pretty reasonable
forget taking oaths. That's my logic, that makes sense." התחיל בר קפרא
לדון. Hitchil Bar Kappara ladun. Bar Kappara says, "Okay, let me tell
you my logic. שבת לכל נאסרה, Shabbos l'chol ne'esra, שבת Shabbos was
forbidden to everyone.
כשיהותרה במקדש הותרה, K'shehutra bamikdash hutra, not for כוהנים. Kohanim. The הלכה
was מלאכה הותרה melacha hutra on שבת Shabbos in the בית המקדש,
Beis HaMikdash, which is pretty funny. I mean Rabbi Chiya's position makes
more sense. I mean anybody can come, I can come into the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and start making a fire?"
"But the only people that can do עבודה Avoda are כוהנים." Kohanim.
"I know, but this is a non-כוהן, Kohen, right?
Right? I mean like any but by definition this person is not
doing עבודה Avoda is what he's saying.
I know, but Bar Kappara is saying that he's only חייב אחת
chayav achas because anytime you're מחלל שבת mechallel Shabbos in the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash it's a dispensation. It's very bizarre, right? He's saying
you're only חייב chayav one? I can go to the בית המקדש,
Beis HaMikdash, light a match. Oh well the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
there's no איסור שבת? issur Shabbos? Okay, exactly." So
yeah, I mean Bar Kappara is very strange. שבת לכל נאסרה כשיהותרה
במקדש הותרה, Shabbos l'chol ne'esra k'shehutra bamikdash hutra, in the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash no problem of שבת. Shabbos. אין כאן אלא זרות. Ein
kan ela zarus. So for a non-כוהן Kohen who does the עבודה,
Avoda, it's only a non-כוהן Kohen doing עבודה, Avoda, forget the שבת
Shabbos problem, שבת Shabbos in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash no problem.
Very strange. Okay. By the way, this does not sound like it's
about איסור חל על איסור, issur chal al issur. it sounds like
it's about how conceptually we understand what does it mean that the
איסור issur of שבת Shabbos was waived in the context of עבודה.
Avoda. Okay, but now we're going to see three debates that are
in parallel. Okay, and seems to be a broader sort of philosophy
is informing all of them. All right, so let's take a look.
בעל מום ששימש בטומאה. Baal mum sheshimesh b'tumah. You have a כוהן
Kohen that has a מום, mum, a blemish. It's אסור assur for
him to serve in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Then he became
טמא. tamei. It's also אסור assur for a טמא tamei person to
serve in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Okay, now this already
more sounds like איסור חל על איסור issur chal al issur because
we're dealing with the איסור issur to serve in the בית המקדש,
Beis HaMikdash, is it אסור assur in one direction or in two
directions? Okay, so let's take a look. רבי חייא אומר חייב שתיים.
Rabbi Chiya omer chayav shtayim. Rabbi Chiya again says, "Boom, you get
both." בר קפרא אומר אינו חייב אלא אחת, Bar Kappara omer eino
chayav ela achas, only one. קפץ רבי חייא ונשבע העבודה כך שמעתי
מרבי שתיים, Kofatz Rabbi Chiya v'nishba ha'avoda kach shamati me'rebi shtayim, right?
By the divine service, this is what I heard from Rebbe, you
get two, you're חייב chayav twice. קפץ בר קפרא ונשבע Kafatz Bar
Kappara ve-nishba, העבודה Ha'avodah! כך שמעתי מרבי אחת. kach shamati me-Rabbi achas.
Okay, I heard I took an oath only one. התחיל רבי חייא
לדון. Hitchil Rabbi Chiya ladun. Fine, let's discuss it. טומאה לכל נאסרה,
Tumah l'chol ne'esra, טומאה Tumah was forbidden to everybody. כשיהותרה במקדש, K'shehutra
bamikdash, now the part that I didn't mention which makes this more
parallel to the שבת Shabbos case is
it's not סתם stam that he's טמא, tamei, it's a קרבן ציבור.
Korban Tzibur. Okay, so טומאה Tumah is allowed in the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash for a קרבן ציבור. Korban Tzibur. So if he was
a normal כוהן, Kohen, he'd be alright to bring the קרבן ציבור
בטומאה, Korban Tzibur b'tumah, right? Okay, but the problem is that he's
a בעל מום. baal mum. So it's similar to the idea of
שבת, Shabbos, which is were you a normal כוהן Kohen you would
have a dispensation. Because you're a בעל מום baal mum you don't.
So therefore do you also transgress the prohibition of טומאה? Tumah? So
let's take a look. Okay.
טומאה לכל נאסרה, Tumah l'chol ne'esra, טומאה Tumah for doing doing עבודה
בטומאה Avoda b'tumah was forbidden to everybody.
כשיהותרה במקדש לכוהנים תמימים הותרה, K'shehutra bamikdash lekohanim tmimim hutra, when it
was given a dispensation because it was a קרבן ציבור, Korban Tzibur,
that dispensation was given to the כוהנים Kohanim who could do the
עבודה. Avoda. לכוהנים תמימים הותרה ולא לבעלי מומים. Lekohanim tmimim hutra v'lo
l'baalei mumim. The dispensation was only to כוהנים Kohanim who could do
the עבודה, Avoda, not to a בעל מום. baal mum. So for
him the prohibition of טומאה Tumah still applies even though it's a
קרבן ציבור. Korban Tzibur. יש כאן משום בעל מום ויש כאן משום
טומאה. Yesh kan mishum baal mum v'yesh kan mishum Tumah. So you
have both prohibitions. התחיל בר קפרא לדון. Hitchil Bar Kappara ladun. Bar
Kappara says, "Let me argue it." טומאה לכל נאסרה, Tumah l'chol ne'esra,
טומאה Tumah was forbidden to everybody. כשיהותרה במקדש במקדש הותרה, K'shehutra bamikdash
bamikdash hutra, when it was allowed because of קרבן ציבור, Korban Tzibur,
it was allowed for anything in the מקדש. Mikdash. And now this
by the way makes a little more sense than שבת. Shabbos. To
say on שבת Shabbos I can walk into the בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash and strike a match seems crazy. To say the idea of
טומאה הותרה בציבור, Tumah hutra b'tzibur, when there's a קרבן ציבור Korban
Tzibur we waive טומאה Tumah concerns and we allow קרבנות Korbanos to
be brought, there there is it makes some sense to say based
also those other discussions in the גמרא Gemara that we saw, that
we sort of like ignore the fact that there's טומאה Tumah once
you're bringing a קרבן ציבור. Korban Tzibur. And then maybe it's not
if anybody were טמא tamei or did the עבודה Avoda whatever, it
would not be an additional prohibition of טומאה. Tumah. We're sort of
like ignoring the problem of טומאה Tumah given that it's a קרבן
ציבור.
Korban
Tzibur.
"קרבן Korban doesn't become טמא?" tamei?
"Well it does, but you can still be מקריב makriv it." The
prohibition is waived. Okay, wait let me see. טומאה לכל נאסרה כשיהותרה
במקדש במקדש הותרה, Tumah l'chol ne'esra k'shehutra bamikdash bamikdash hutra, in anything
done in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, טומאה Tumah by a קרבן
ציבור Korban Tzibur we're ignoring it. אין כאן אלא משום בעל מום,
Ein kan ela mishum baal mum, so there's no prohibition of
טומאה. Tumah.
Let's say
I don't know everybody is טמא מת tamei meis or something. There
was a war and everybody got טמא מת tamei meis or everybody
whatever. So all the כהנים kohanim are טמאים. tmei'im. Okay, but it's
a קרבן ציבור korban tzibur it has to be brought.
Good, so I'll say what's the distinction between they are arguing whether
a כהן kohen who is טמא tamei who is already טמא tamei
can bring.
No, כהן kohen who is טמא tamei can bring a קרבן ציבור.
korban tzibur. But let's say this כהן kohen who is טמא tamei
is also a בעל מום ba'al mum so he's excluded anyway from
bringing קרבנות. korbanos.
Okay, so he transgresses bringing a בעל מום ba'al mum who does
the עבודה. avodah. Does he also transgress being a טמא tamei person
doing the עבודה avodah or in this context טומאה tumah is irrelevant?
Okay?
So the גמרא Gemara. says like this, third case, זה שאכל מליקה.
zeh she-achal melikah. So you go ahead and the כהן kohen does
the, brings the קרבן korban of the bird, the bird חטאת, chatas,
and he uses his fingernail to pierce it from behind
the neck. Now if that were not a legitimate קרבן, korban, it
would be a נבלה. neveilah. It would be a bird that died
without a kosher שחיטה. shechitah. So this person now is a non-כהן.
kohen. It is a kosher קרבן, korban, a כהן kohen did it
and brought it and it's a kosher קרבן. korban. See, but it
can, it's a חטאת, chatas, it can only be eaten by כהנים.
kohanim. He's a non-כהן. kohen. He's not allowed to eat a חטאת.
chatas. He goes ahead and he eats this חטאת chatas bird. He
certainly transgresses eating a חטאת, chatas, did he also transgress eating נבלה?
neveilah? Because it is a נבלה. neveilah. Okay? So זה שאכל מליקה,
zeh she-achal melikah, רבי חייא אומר חייב שתים, Rabbi Chiya omer chayav
shtayim, ובר קפרא אומר אינו חייב אלא אחת. u-Bar Kappara omer eino
chayav ella achas. קפץ רבי חייא ונשבע, Kafatz Rabbi Chiya ve-nishba, העבודה,
ha-avodah, כך שמעתי מרבי Kach shamati meRebbi שתים. shta'im. קפץ Kafatz בר
קפרא Bar Kappara ונשבע, venishba. העבודה, ha-avodah, כך שמעתי מרבי Kach shamati
meRebbi אחת. achat. התחיל רבי חייא לדון, Hitchil Rabbi Chiya ladun,
נבלה לכל נאסרה. neveilah le-chol ne'esra. נבלה Neveilah was forbidden to all.
כשהותרה Kshehutra במקדש beMikdash, when it was allowed in the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash by a bird קרבן, korban, אצל כהנים הותרה etzel kohanim
hutra it was permitted by כהנים. kohanim. לכהנים הותרה ולא לזרים le-kohanim
hutra velo le-zarim for this guy who is a non-כהן kohen it
remains being a נבלה. neveilah. יש כאן משום זרות ויש כאן משום
מליקה.
yesh kan mishum zarus ve-yesh
kan mishum melikah. התחיל בר קפרא לדון, Hitchil Bar Kappara ladun, נבלה
לכל נאסרה, neveilah le-chol ne'esra, כשהותרה במקדש כשהותרה במקדש הותרה. keshe-hutra be-mikdash
keshe-hutra be-mikdash hutra. No, when the Torah said this is how you
bring a bird קרבן, korban, it basically said if you do it
like this, it's not a נבלה. neveilah. So there actually, what בר
קפרא Bar Kappara says makes reasonable sense, right? You could see all
of these things as being local questions, not a, although it is
interesting that they have it in three places. But if I asked
you, when you did the case of the bird מליקה, melikah, right,
is it a נבלה neveilah or is the Torah saying if you
do it this way and you bring it as this type of
קרבן korban it's not a נבלה? neveilah? It makes a lot of
sense to say it's not a נבלה neveilah which is מותר mutter
to כהנים. kohanim. In this case, it's not a נבלה, neveilah, right?
Or but again, so that makes sense in this case. Lighting a
match in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash on שבת Shabbos presumably we
say no, שבת Shabbos still applies in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash,
it's just a special allowance if you're doing the עבודה, avodah, right?
So there's different ways that you could come to different conclusions in
these cases. Is it you basically have the problem but it's a
special allowance for כהנים kohanim doing the עבודה, avodah, or is the
Torah saying in this case it's like the problem doesn't exist? Okay,
but that what seems to be the debate in these three cases,
how do you conceptualize it? כשהותרה במקדש הותרה, keshe-hutra be-mikdash hutra, אין
כאן אלא משום זרות. ein kan ella mishum zarus. So it seems
like as I said, they are three parallel but in a certain
way local debates about how do you understand the nature of these
allowances. Allowing טומאה בציבור, tumah be-tzibur, allowing עבודה avodah on שבת, Shabbos,
allowing eating the dead bird. Do you understand it as if the
problem doesn't exist at all in these contexts or it's a special
allowance in the context when you're a כהן kohen doing the עבודה
avodah in the right way? And that would be the question, do
you get punished twice or only punished once? But the גמרא Gemara
is going to interpret this to be about the question of both
איסורין, issurin, does one איסור issur take effect on the other איסור?
issur Okay, so that's how the גמרא Gemara is going to rephrase
this. במאי קמיפלגי? be-mai kamiflagi? Yes.
Does everybody hold that מליקה melikah is not a type of שחיטה
shechitah and it produces a נבלה? neveilah?
Well that's exactly what we're asking. If it weren't in the context
of קרבן korban everybody would hold that for sure, right? So that's
exactly what we're debating. In the context of קרבן korban how do
you conceptualize it? Is it a נבלה neveilah that's מותר mutter for
כהנים kohanim to eat or is it not a נבלה? neveilah? That's
exactly the question. Again, so I would have said it's a local
question, how do you conceptualize מליקה melikah of a
bird when it's done properly? But the גמרא Gemara is going to
say since these are all three parallel debates, let's not look at
them as local debates, let's look at them as a larger question
of איסור חל על איסור. issur chal al issur, So let's take
a look. Top of לג עמוד א. lamed gimmel amud aleph. במאי
קמיפלגי, be-mai kamiflagi, what's at the heart of this debate? באיסור כולל
ואליבא דרבי יוסי. be-issur kolel ve-aliba de-Rabbi Yossi. It's a question of
איסור כולל issur kolel according to רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yose. We're assuming
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi, who is prepared to say איסור חל על
איסור issur chal al issur. by איסור מוסיף issur mosif as we
saw before, will he also say it by איסור כולל? issur kolel?
And these are cases of איסור כולל. issur kolel.
רבי חייא סבר רבי יוסי באיסור כולל מחייב. Rabbi Chiya savar Rabbi
Yossi be-issur kolel mechayev. רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya says two by all
these cases, he's going to define all these cases as an איסור
כולל issur kolel and say since רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi is the
one who is prepared sometimes to say איסור חל על איסור, issur
chal al issur we'll say that he says it even in a
case of איסור כולל, issur kolel, מחייב תרתי, mechayev tartei, and all
these cases are איסור כולל issur kolel and that's why you get
two. בר קפרא Bar Kappara סבר savar לא מחייב אלא חדא. lo
mechayev ela chada. No, only one, even according to רבי יוסי. Rabbi
Yosi ומאי איסור כולל איכא, umai issur kollel ika, where's the איסור
כולל? issur kollel? הכא hacha בשלמא bishlama זר zar מעיקרא me-ikara שרי
במלאכה shari b'melacha ואסור בעבודה. v'assur b'avoda. So let's go in order.
The case of a זר zar that does the עבודה avoda on
שבת. Shabbos. A
זר, zar, initially, he can do, he can do מלאכה melacha during
the week, it's a Tuesday, he can go ahead and light a
match, but he can't do עבודה avoda in the בית המקדש. Beis
HaMikdash. אתיא לשבת, Asya l'Shabbos, שבת Shabbos comes along. מיגו דקמיתסר במלאכה
מיתסר נמי בעבודה. migo d'kamitra b'melacha mitrah nami b'avoda. Since he can't
do other מלאכה, melacha, he also can't do the עבודה. avoda. So
again, to use my איסור כולל issur kollel איסור מוסיף issur mosif
motif, איסור כולל issur kollel is you broaden the class. Okay, so
here's your זר. zar. Okay,
here's your זר. zar.
He is not allowed to do, here, he is allowed to do
מלאכה, melacha, the one thing he can't do is עבודה avoda in
the מקדש. Mikdash. Okay, that's what he can't do. עבודה avoda in
the מקדש, Mikdash, that's forbidden to him.
That's the one thing that he can't do. Comes along שבת, Shabbos,
that's on Sunday. This is on Sunday. He can't do עבודה avoda
in the מקדש. Mikdash. Comes along שבת Shabbos and שבת Shabbos says,
oh, now that it's שבת, Shabbos, you know what else you can't
do? You can't do any of the
ל"ט מלאכות. lamed-tes melachos. So now, has the עבודה avoda in the
בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, here we'll make a little, we'll make a
little מזבח mizbe'ach here with a fire or whatever, has the עבודה
avoda in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash become forbidden to a broader
scope of people? No. What's happened is there's a wider class of
things that cannot be done. עבודה avoda in all can't be done,
which includes also the עבודה avoda in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash.
So this status hasn't broadened, which would be מוסיף, mosif, the class
of things that cannot be done has broadened, and therefore because the
ל"ט מלאכות lamed-tes melachos in general can't be done, should that also
say that that status also applies to עבודה avoda in the מקדש?
Mikdash? It's now not only אסור assur from the perspective of עבודה
avoda of a non-כהן, kohen, it's also אסור assur from the perspective
of עבודה avoda on שבת. Shabbos.
So איסור כולל issur kollel is you either find yourself now in
a bigger population of people to whom this one איסור issur applies,
or this one person finds himself...
No, bigger population of people is
מוסיף. mosif. מוסיף mosif means,
if
my visuals aren't helping, מוסיף mosif means more people are forbidden. Maybe
this is an easier way of thinking it, be a little more
concrete. כולל kollel means more activities are forbidden.
So in the case of the sister, because the wife's sister becomes
brother's wife, more people are forbidden. The scope of her status affects
more people. Other brothers can't marry her. That's more people are forbidden.
In the case where brother's wife becomes wife's sister, more people aren't
forbidden. He cannot marry a wider range of people. He cannot marry
the other sisters as well. So more activities are forbidden. Not only
with... So here, this is not forbidden on more people, that would
be איסור מוסיף. issur mosif. It's he can't do other things as
well. He also can't do ל"ט מלאכות lamed-tes melachos outside of the
מקדש. Mikdash. So I don't know if that helps to think about
it as that way, the difference of מוסיף mosif is more people,
the scope applies, it's a scope of larger people, here it's a
scope of larger activities. But I actually think the difference is, as
that this focuses on if you would the חפצא, cheftza, although we're
talking about people, the object that's forbidden, and the object that's forbidden,
its scope has broadened. That's איסור מוסיף. issur mosif. This, the object
that's forbidden, be it a person, be it the עבודה avoda in
the מקדש, Mikdash, that scope has not broadened, but the person who
is prohibited now cannot do a wider range of things.
So this is broadening the scope of the חפצא cheftza and this
is broadening the activity of the גברא. gavra. Again, I'm using a
lot of different terms. If any of those help you, or if
I'm just confusing... looks like I'm succeeding in confusing.
No, I think about something else.
In a sense, anybody who has... there's always an איסור מוסיף. issur
mosif. This question is a little bit ridiculous. Yes, you know, a
זר, zar, the day he's born he's אסור assur to do the
עבודה. avoda. Twenty years later, there's a billion more people in the
world.
Yes, but that's similar, that's the reverse of Michael's question of let's
say there are no more sisters, then let's say there can't be
more sisters, father and mother are dead and so on. So it's
all about conceptual, it's not about practically whether there are things. So
let's see, let's see the גמרא. Gemara: That we get. בשלמא bishlama
זר zar מעיקרא me-ikara שרי במלאכה shari b'melacha ואסור בעבודה. v'assur b'avoda.
אתיא לשבת, Asya la'Shabbos, שבת Shabbos comes along. מיגו דקא מיתסר במלאכה,
Migo de-ka mitasar be'melacha, now it's אסור asur to do מלאכה melacha
in all realms, מיתסר נמי בעבודה, mitasar nami be'avoda, so the עבודה
avoda also becomes אסור asur again from a שבת Shabbos perspective. But
בעל מום מעיקרא, Baal Mum meikara, שרי באכילה. shari ba'achila. Now let's
say you have a כהן kohen that has a מום. mum. So
he's not allowed to do the עבודה, avoda, but he's allowed to
eat the קרבנות. korbanot. ואסור בעבודה. Ve'asur be'avoda. איתמלא, It-mela, he becomes
טמא. tamei. מיגו, Migo, so it's not that עבודה avoda is now
אסור asur to more people. No, he can now not do a
wider range of activities. איתמלא, It-mela, he becomes טמא. tamei. מיגו דקא
מיתסר באכילה, Migo de-ka mitasar ba'achila, since now he can't eat קרבנות,
korbanot, right? Because a בעל מום Baal Mum can eat קרבנות, korbanot,
but a טמא tamei person cannot. So מיתסר נמי בעבודה, mitasar nami
be'avoda, so that also now schleps along the עבודה avoda as well.
Okay? So replace עבודה במקדש avoda be'mikdash and here you have a
case of, if you are a
בעל מום, Baal Mum, and this was
about... yeah. So he was אסור בעבודה. asur be'avoda. My bad, I
was looking at the wrong עמוד. amud. Okay, so same point. A
בעל מום Baal Mum can't do the עבודה, avoda, but he could
eat קרבנות. korbanot. Okay? Once he comes along and gets טמא, tamei,
now that he became טמא, tamei, he can also not eat קרבנות.
korbanot. Okay? So since
now... this is a little bit different because by the case of
ל"ט מלאכות, Lamed Tet Melachot, if you did the עבודה avoda in
the מקדש, Mikdash, you're both doing the איסור עבודה issur avoda and
the broader category of איסור מלאכה, issur melacha, right? Here it's a
little different because his status of becoming טמא tamei prohibited him from
קרבנות korbanot from the eating perspective, it also is going to affect
קרבנות korbanot from
the
doing
perspective.
Is that a general principle that someone who is אסור באכילה asur
ba'achila is אסור בעבודה? asur be'avoda? Generally, yes.
Because, yes, so it
assumes this is a sociological construct.
Yeah, I'm not sure you have to say that to make this
logic work, but generally that's true, that is true. Anyway the גמרא
Gemara... says like this: That we get. We get how you can
say כולל kolel in both of those cases.
אלא מליקה בבת אחת היא דמשכחת לה. Ella Melika be'vat achat hi
de-mishkachat lah. באיסור כולל לא משכחת לה. Be'issur kolel lo mishkachat lah.
But the גמרא Gemara says מליקה, Melika, you never get a sequence.
The כהן kohen did מליקה, Melika, right? What, this bird all of
a sudden becomes נבלה neveila and it also becomes a קרבן korban
that's אסור asur to זרים. zarim. So in the very second that
he became forbidden in this bird, he wasn't forbidden in the bird
before מליקה—I Melika mean, he was, it's an איסור מעילה—but issur meila
the specific איסור of a זר zar to eat a קרבן korban
is only the moment it becomes a קרבן. korban. So the moment
he does מליקה, Melika, introduced two איסורים issurim at the exact same
time. The איסור of נבלה neveila and the איסור of a non-כהן
kohen eating a קרבן. korban. So there's no sequence. So what could
the debate be in that case? Okay?
So, דמשכחת לה באיסור כולל לא משכחת לה. de-mishkachat lah be'issur kolel
lo mishkachat lah. So it can't be that they're debating the איסור
of איסור כולל issur kolel because that could not apply to the
case of מליקה. Melika. So let's try again. אלא, Ella, fine. Let's
say this is what they're debating. קמיפלגי באיסור בבת אחת. Kamaspleigi be'issur
be'vat achat. They're debating what happens if it happens at the same
time. Can you get two איסורים issurim if they're coming exactly at
one? אליבא דרבי יוסי, Aliba d'Rabbi Yosi, and according to רבי יוסי,
Rebbi Yossi again רבי יוסי Rebbi Yossi we know says you can
get two איסורים issurim if the second one is מוסיף. mosif. What
about if there's no second? What about if they're simultaneous? Would רבי
יוסי Rebbi Yossi say you could get two איסורים? issurim? רבי חייא
סבר רבי יוסי באיסור בבת אחת מחייב תרתי, Rabbi Chiya savar Rabbi
Yosi be'issur be'vat achat mechayev tartei, if they come at once you
can get punished twice. ובר קפרא סבר לא מחייב אלא חדא, U'Bar
Kappara savar lo mechayev ela chada, only one. Now how do you
get coming at once? The case of the bird, we said it
comes at once. As soon as it becomes a נבלה, neveila, it
becomes a kosher קרבן korban and there's an איסור of זרות. zarus.
But how about these cases, how do they come at once? So
the
גמרא Gemara says: והכא מאי בבת אחת איכא? ve-hacha mai be'vat achat
ika? הכא, Hacha, so זר ששימש בשבת, zar she-shimesh be'Shabbos, if it's
the case of a זר zar doing the עבודה avoda on שבת,
Shabbos, right? So we already said before שבת Shabbos rolled around, he
was already אסור asur in the עבודה. avoda. So where do you
get him becoming אסור asur in the עבודה avoda and אסור asur
on שבת Shabbos at the same moment? Right? Because Friday it wasn't
both. So listen to the גמרא: Gemara כגון דאייתי שתי שערות בשבת.
K'gon de-aisi shtei se'arot be'Shabbos. He became an adult on שבת. Shabbos.
Now you can't say he had his bar mitzvah on שבת Shabbos
because that begins at the beginning of the day. Actually maybe the
גמרא... Gemara Maybe
it could have said that too. But anyway, he got his two
pubic hairs on שבת. Shabbos. So at the very moment he became
an adult, it was already שבת Shabbos and he both couldn't do
the עבודה avoda of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and he couldn't
do מלאכה melacha on שבת. Shabbos. So that's sort of like the
questions you were asking today, Hope. So at that moment, that's the
time when you get both at the same time. Okay, so that's
the case for that.
Where are we?
דהוו להו זרות ושבת בהדי הדדי. de'havu lehu zarus ve'shabbos ba'hadi hadadi.
Now בעל מום Baal Mum נמי, nami, how is the case about
a בעל מום Baal Mum that you get them both at the
same time? Okay, כגון דאייתי שתי שערות ומום ליה. kegon de'asai se'aros
ve'moom leh. He got two שערות, se'aros, he had been טמא, tamei,
he had been טמא tamei but he wasn't yet an adult. And
the moment that he became an adult, that he got his two
pubic hairs, he became and he had a blemish, he became אסור
assur both to do the עבודה avoda because he had a blemish
and to do the עבודה avoda because he was טמא. tamei. So
it happened at the exact same time because when he became an
adult, both of the things were current statuses. Okay,
דהוו ליה בעל מום וטומאה בהדי הדדי. de'havu leh baal mum ve'tumah
ba'hadi hadadi. They come at the same time. אי נמי, I nami,
or you could say, and this is a little bit more of
a fun case as instead of having to rely on the moment
he became an adult. שחתכת אצבעו בסכין טמאה. shechatchat etzba'o besakin tmea.
He cut his
finger with a טמא tamei knife. So at the very moment he
became טמא, tamei, he became a בעל מום. Baal Mum. Okay. So,
alright. Off, right, exactly. Okay. So now we can create construct, again,
it's not at all פשט pshat of the three cases. The three
cases need to be much more general issues, but we can now
construct the scenario where all three of them are where all three
cases happened at the same time. And we could say that's the
debate of רבי חייא Rebbi Chiya and בר קפרא, Bar Kappara, when
they happen at the same time do you get two or do
you get one? So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says like
this.
בשלמא לרבי חייא, Bishlama le'Rebbi Chiya, works according to רבי חייא, Rebbi
Chiya, כי אתני לדידיה, ki asnei l'didei, now the גמרא Gemara is
going to understand like this. How could it happen that both רבי
חייא Rebbi Chiya and בר קפרא Bar Kappara are taking opposite oaths
about what רבי Rebbi, said? I mean, רבי Rebbi said one thing.
So it must be that somebody misunderstood. Now you could also say
maybe רבי Rebbi changed his mind, but the גמרא Gemara doesn't want
to say that. It must be somebody misunderstood. So we're going to
try to reconstruct what could have happened to have led to this
misunderstanding. Okay, so let's take a look. בשלמא לרבי חייא, Bishlama le'Rebbi
Chiya, according to רבי חייא Rebbi Chiya I got it where scenario
בת אחת bas achas and he understood that רבי Rebbi said that
you get two איסורים. issurim. So it makes sense how בר קפרא
Bar Kappara could have made a mistake. Why? כי אתני לדידיה אליבא
דרבי יוסי, ki asnai l'didei aliba de'Rebbi Yossi, because when רבי Rebbi
taught, said you get חייב chayiv twice, so he was saying according
to רבי יוסי Rebbi Yossi you get חייב chayiv twice. And that's
why רבי חייא Rebbi Chiya heard you're חייב chayiv twice. כי אתני
לבר קפרא, ki asnai le'Bar Kappara, when רבי Rebbi taught בר קפרא
Bar Kappara and said you're only חייב chayiv once, אליבא דרבי שמעון,
aliba de'Rebbi Shimon, he was teaching it according to רבי שמעון Rebbi
Shimon that you're only חייב chayiv once. And there because רבי שמעון
Rebbi Shimon generally holds that you don't say איסור חל על איסור.
issur chal al issur, So רבי חייא Rebbi Chiya can understand the
message he got and the mistake בר קפרא Bar Kappara made. אלא
לבר קפרא, Ela le'Bar Kappara, but according to בר קפרא, Bar Kappara,
he understands that רבי Rebbi told him that according to even according
to רבי יוסי Rebbi Yossi. you only get once when it's the
same time. So what did רבי חייא Rebbi Chiya think? רבי חייא
Rebbi Chiya heard twice. Where was he getting that idea if בר
קפרא Bar Kappara thinks that רבי Rebbi taught him that even according
to רבי יוסי Rebbi Yossi. it's only once, how could what did
he hear? No, רבי יוסי Rebbi Yossi. is the one who allows
for the possibility of twice. Meaning רבי חייא Rebbi Chiya said I
heard from רבי Rebbi you get twice, that was according to רבי
יוסי. Rebbi Yossi I think where בר קפרא Bar Kappara went wrong
is he probably heard when רבי Rebbi was talking according to רבי
שמעון, Rebbi Shimon, according to רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon it would be
only once. But בר קפרא Bar Kappara says no, I heard from
רבי Rebbi twice and I believe that was according to I heard
from רבי Rebbi once and I believe that was according to רבי
יוסי. Rebbi Yossi. So then so what did רבי חייא Rebbi Chiya
hear of twice, right? There's no option according to you of twice.
So the גמרא says like this. אלא לבר קפרא, Ela le'Bar Kappara,
רבי חייא שקרי קמשקר? Rebbi Chiya shikrei ka mishaker? Is רבי חייא
Rebbi Chiya lying that he's swearing
that רבי Rebbi said twice? I mean again, so funny the גמרא
asks it this way, but the גמרא is taken by the fact
that they're taking oaths. So they really think what they're saying is
you know what they heard. So again, maybe the always answer always
could be he's not lying, he misheard, רבי Rebbi changed his mind,
but it doesn't want to say that. It wants to explain what
could have led to the confusion. So the גמרא says אלא ela
fine. We're not arguing about בת אחת bas achas according to רבי
יוסי. Rabbi Yosei. אלא קמיפלגי באיסור בת אחת אליבא דרבי שמעון, ela
kamifligi be'issur bas achas aliba de'Rebbi Shimon, which makes sense. You know
what? רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei is prepared to say איסור חל על
איסור even if it's sequential. We're going to say that the question
is רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon who normally holds אין איסור חל על
איסור, ein issur chal al issur, maybe he could hold it when
it's at the same time because then they're not competing, they're coming
at the same time. So it's the same thing we said before
except we're saying the debate is in רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon, not
in רבי Rebbi יוסי. And that'll help in explaining how this error
crept in. Let's just read one more sentence about this.
באיסור בת אחת אליבא דרבי שמעון. be'issur bas achas aliba de'Rebbi Shimon.
בשלמא... Bishlama... now it makes sense according to
רבי חייא. Rabbi Chiya. קא משתבע לאפוקי דרבי שמעון מחזקיה. Ka mishtaba
le'afukei deRabbi Shimon meChezkiah. So רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya swearing and he's
saying even though you think רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon never holds of
איסור חל על איסור, I'm going to swear that you get twice
even according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon because it's בבת אחת. bevas
achat. אלא לבר קפרא למה לי לאשתבועי? Ela leBar Kappara lama lei
le'ishtabuyei? Why is he swearing? All בר קפרא Bar Kappara saying is
no, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon just holds what he normally holds, you're
only חייב chayav once. So you don't have to swear. I mean,
that's their normal opinion at all, that's, ditto, you're only חייב chayav
once. All right, קשיא. That's difficult. But whatever, we're not going to
get hung up on that. I mean, everybody's excited, so everybody swears.
Now we're going to get back to our other question. בשלמא לבר
קפרא, Bishlama leBar Kappara, now I get according to בר קפרא Bar
Kappara where the mistake crept in. He would say, כי אתנייה רבי
לדידי, Ki asnayei Rabbi ledidi, when רבי Rabbi taught him once, אליבא
דרבי שמעון, aliba deRabbi Shimon, it was according to רבי שמעון. Rabbi
Shimon. And now, but he understands where רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya went
wrong. כי אתנייה לרבי חייא, Ki asnayei leRabbi Chiya, when רבי Rabbi
taught רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya and רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya heard twice,
that was אליבא דרבי יוסי. aliba deRabbi Yosei. I can understand רבי
חייא Rabbi Chiya where you went wrong. I understand you heard twice,
but that was according to רבי Rabbi יוסי. We're talking here according
to רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. And I'm telling you רבי Rabbi said
according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon only once. So now you understand
from בר קפרא'ס Bar Kappara's perspective where רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya went
wrong. But we have now the same question we had before, except
reversed. אלא לרבי חייא, Ela leRabbi Chiya, but according to רבי חייא,
Rabbi Chiya, he thinks that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon taught him that
רבי Rabbi taught him according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon even according
to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon twice. So how did בר קפרא Bar
Kappara hear once? אלא לרבי חייא בר קפרא שיקורי קמשקר? Ela leRabbi
Chiya Bar Kappara shikurei kamshakar? You think בר קפרא Bar Kappara is
lying? Okay, so we got we have a way of explaining it
that they're debating what would be the status if it happened at
the same time. Either according to רבי יוסי or according to רבי
שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. But the problem is in either way of framing
it, it's not you can't really explain how a mistake was made
in both directions, how either side could believe the other side made
a legitimate mistake. And we have to believe it was a legitimate
mistake, that it wasn't that רבי changed his mind, and wasn't that
somebody misheard, it was a different type of a context. And that
won't work in both directions.
So we will pick up and look at the answer for this
tomorrow. All right, כח. koach.